Guide to the Karen Horney Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Karen Horney papers
1899-1999
MS 1604
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, writings, and photographs documenting the life of Karen Horney. Also included are lecture notes, memoirs and recollections, interview notes, and audiocassettes.
Horney, Karen, 1885-1952
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in box 3 of the original accession are restricted due to their physical nature. Researchers are required to use the preservation photocopies in Box 1 rather than the originals.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Renate Patterson, 1991, 1995, and 2000; Dr. Marianne H. von Eckardt, 1991; Bernard J. Paris, 1991-1992, and 1999; and Dr. Jeffrey Rubin, Dean, American Institute for Psychoanalysis of the Karen Horney Psychoanalytic Institute and Center, 1991 and 1997; Mimi Sheiner, 1999.
Biographical / Historical
Karen Danielson Horney was born in Hamburg, Germany, on September 16, 1885. She received her medical degree in 1909 from the University of Berlin. In the same year she married Oskar Horney, a Berlin attorney, from whom she was divorced in 1937. From 1914 to 1918 Karen Horney studied at the Berlin-Lankwitz Psychoanalytic Institute, and it was during this time that she participated with Sigmund Freud in discussions on psychological analysis by non-physicians. Dr. Horney left Germany for the United States in 1932, and became the associate director for the Chicago Institute of Psychoanalysis. From 1934 to 1941, she was on the teaching staff of the New York Psychoanalytic Institute. In 1941 Dr. Horney was one of the founders of the American Psychoanalytic Institute, and helped start the Association for the Advancement of Psychoanalysis. She died in New York on December 4, 1952.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, writings, and photographs documenting the life of Karen Horney. Also included are lecture notes, memoirs and recollections, interview notes, and audiocassettes.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by accession.
Psychiatry; Psychoanalysis; Psychoanalysts; Horney, Karen, 1885-1952
- Original accession
  - Typescript of letters from Karen Danielson to Oskar Horney, 1906-1907 (Box 1)
  - Typescript (in German) of Karen Horney's adolescent diaries, 1899-1912 (Box 1)
  - Preservation photocopies of the adolescent diaries, 5 volumes:
    - 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1902 (labelled 1900-1901 on spine) (Box 1)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 1)
    - 1904-1907 (labelled 1900-1907 on spine) (Box 1)
    - 1910-1912 (labelled 1910-1911 on spine) (Box 1)
  - Preservation photocopy of Ego Notebook (labelled "Diary 1906-1907" on spine), 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Preservation photocopy of notebook on children (in pamphlet binding, identified as "Diary, 1912-1918"), 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of four uncollected essays in German by Karen Horney:
    - "Der Männlichkeitskomplex der Frau" ("The Masculinity Complex in Women"). Archiv für Frauenkunde > 13 (1927): 141-154 (Box 1)
    - "Über die psychischen Wurzeln einiger typischer Ehekonflikte" ("On the Psychic Origins of Some Typical Marriage Problems"), Ein Biologisches Ehebuch, ed. M. Marcuse. Berlin: Marcus & Weber, 1927 (Box 1)
    - "Psychische Eignung and Nichteignung zur Ehe" ("Psychic Fitness and Unfitness for Marriage"). Ein Biologisches Ehebuch, ed. M. Marcuse. Berlin: Marcus & Weber, 1927 (Box 1)
    - "Über die psychischen Bestimmungen der Gattenwahl" ("On the Psychic Determinants of Choosing a Partner"). Ein Biologisches Ehebuch, ed. M. Marcuse. Berlin: Marcus & Weber, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Reprints of nine essays (with four duplicates) in German by Karen Horney, 1917-1951 (Box 1)
  - Photocopy of manuscript, "Pride and Self-Hatred in Neurosis", 1947 (Box 1)
  - Photographs:
    - Horney, Karen (Box 1)
    - Horney, Oskar (Box 1)
    - Danielson family (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - Karen Horney Clinic (Box 1)
    - Negatives (Box 1)
  - Notes on Karen Horney's lectures, Chicago and Washington, 1933-1935 (Box 2)
  - Memoirs and recollections:
    - Blitzsten, Dorothy: copy of memoir, "Lionel Blitzsten and the Chicago Psychoanalytic Scene, 1932-1934," and "Notes on H.S. Sullivan and Horney", undated (Box 2)
    - De Rosis, Helen: copy of unpublished essay, "Karen Horney--Optimist and Liberationist", 1971 (Box 2)
    - Graber, Gustav Hans: memoir, undated (Box 2)
    - Kondo, Akihisa: copy of "Recollections of Dr. Horney", 1974 (Box 2)
    - Lederer-Eckardt, Gertrude: copy of memoir of her experience with Karen Horney, 1958-1973 (Box 2)
    - Moulton, Ruth: copy of "Memories of My Analytic Training", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photocopies of interview notes by Jack Rubins for biography of Karen Horney (Box 2)
  - Research materials collected by Jack Rubins, including folders on individuals, articles, reviews, and eulogies:
    - Eckardt, Marianne Horney (Box 2)
    - Grinker, Roy R. (Box 2)
    - Horney, Brigitte (Box 2)
    - Horney, Karen (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Kardiner, Abram (Box 2)
    - Kubie, Lawrence (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lorand, Sandor (Box 2)
    - Martin, Alexander (Box 2)
    - Mead, Margaret (Box 2)
    - Patterson, Renate Horney (Box 2)
    - Rado, Sandor (Box 2)
    - Tillich, Hannah (Box 2)
    - Weigert, Edith (Box 2)
    - Association for the Advancement of Psychoanalysis (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Articles-Other Analysts, etc. (Box 2)
    - Eulogies (Box 2)
    - History of psychoanalytic institutes (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Horney's history with institutes (Box 2)
    - Müller-Braunschweig, Hans to Rubins (Box 2)
    - Psychoanalysis in Germany (Box 2)
    - Rubins correspondence (Box 2)
  - Restricted material
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials in box 3 of the original accession are restricted due to their physical nature. Researchers are required to use the preservation photocopies in Box 1 rather than the originals.
    - Letters from Karen Danielsen to Oskar Horney, 1906-1907 (Box 3)
    - Adolescent diaries, in German, 5 volumes.
      - 1899, 1 volume (encapsulated in mylar, bound, and boxed) (Box 3)
      - 1900-1902, 1 volume (encapsulated in mylar, bound, and boxed) (Box 3)
      - 1903-1904, 1 volume (in custom-made box) (Box 3)
      - 1904-1907, 1 volume (in custom-made box) (Box 3)
      - 1910-1912, 1 volume (in custom-made box) (Box 3)
    - Ego Notebook, 1906-, in German, 1 volume (in custom made box) (Box 3)
    - Notebook on children, 1912-1918, in German, 1 volume (in custom made box) (Box 3)
    - Blank diaries, 2 volumes (in custom-made boxes) (Box 3)
    - Microfilm of the diaries and notebooks, 3 reels (Box 3)
- Additional Material, 1906-1970s, undated; Accession 1993-M-010; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1992 Sep
  Received from: Bernard Paris, 1992 Jul 23
  - Academic and professional certificates, 1906-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Marriage certificate, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of recommendation on behalf of Karen Horney for admittance to the United States, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of Accuracy: translations of official papers (2 copies), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Educational and Scientific Record of Dr. Karen Horney," one page autobiography, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original interview notes by Jack Rubins for biography of Karen Horney, Early 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, undated; Accession 1995-M-120; 1
  Addition inventory by Diane E. Kaplan 1995 Mar
  Received from: Renate Horney Patterson, 1995 Mar 9
  - My Life with Mother by Renate Horney Patterson, undated
    General note
    See: box 1 (shelved with Acc. 1993-M-010)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-154
  This addition consists of Karen Horney's lecture notes for the course Psychoanalytic Techniques, which she offered at the American Institute for Psychoanalysis in New York City. Horney gave the lectures in succeeding years from 1950-1952.
  Folder titles are transcribed from the labels Horney wrote on the front of the original folders. Illegible words and undeciphered abbreviations are indicated by an underlined blank space. The folders are arranged by year and then by the Roman numerals Horney assigned. Folders without Roman numerals are organized at the end of the year. Undated folders are arranged at the end of the accession. Those with Roman numerals are arranged first followed by those without. Some notes may have been used for more than one lecture.
  - 1950
    - I. Aims of Psychoanalytic Therapy (Box 1)
    - II. Dreams (Box 1)
    - III. Specific psychoanalytic means of understanding (Box 1)
    - IV. Specific--Understanding (II) (Box 1)
    - VI. [no title] (Box 1)
    - VIII. Personal Equation (Box 1)
    - Retarding forces--Defenses--Blockages (Box 1)
  - 1951
    - II. Dreams--final presentation (Box 1)
    - XV. Dealing with Conflict (Box 1)
    - Dealing with Conflict (Box 1)
  - 1952
    - I. Aims (Box 1)
    - II. Diagnostic value--Preliminary Interviews (Box 1)
    - III. Interviews ________ (Box 1)
    - IV. Prognostic Value (Box 1)
    - V. Patient's attitude toward psychoanalysis--incentives and reservations (Box 1)
    - VI. Practical arrangements (Box 1)
    - VII. Essentials of psychoanalytic ________ (Box 1)
  - 1952-1953
    - I. Quality of Analyst's Attention (Box 1)
    - II. Free association--specific psychoanalytic means (Box 1)
    - III-IV. Understanding the Patient (Box 1)
    - IV. Nature of blockages, Difficulties and Defenses (Box 1)
    - V. Difficulties and Defenses-- ________Psychoanalytic Relationship (Box 1)
    - VIII. Interpreting Meaning and Crisis (Box 1)
  - no date
    - II. Self-Psychoanalysis of Analyst (Box 1)
    - II. Understanding the Patient (Box 1)
    - III. Preliminary Interviews, The Diagnostic Value (Box 1)
    - IV. History, Therapeutic Value (Box 1)
    - V. Therapeutic Value (Box 1)
    - VII and II. [no titles] (Box 1)
    - X. Form of block (Box 1)
    - XI. Psychoanalytic relationship (Box 1)
    - XIII. Interpretation and Timing (Box 1)
    - XV. Transference (Box 1)
    - XXV. Termination (Box 1)
    - Detailed sequence of some sessions, Big sweeping movements (Box 1)
    - Quality of Analyst's understanding (Box 1)
    - What Is Neurosis? (Box 1)
    - Monogame Forderung Problematik (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1914-1993; Accession 2000-M-091
  - Reviews of Self-Analysis, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Handwritten notes on Madame Bovary [for course Horney taught at the New School for Social Research], undated (Box 1)
  - "Enslavement in Marriage", undated (Box 1)
  - "Notes on Fear", [193-] (Box 1)
  - "Sadistic Love" [notes and printed summary of lecture], 1943 (Box 1)
  - "The Achievement of Freud", undated (Box 1)
  - "Understanding Personal Difficulties in a Period of Social Transition", 1938 (Box 1)
  - Our Inner Conflicts
    - "The Need for Human Intimacy" [draft of Chapter 3], undated (Box 1)
    - "Consequences of Unsolved Conflicts--Resulting Fears" [draft of Chapter 9], undated (Box 1)
  - "The Misuse of Psychoanalysis", undated (Box 1)
  - "Restricted Applications of Psychoanalysis to Social Work", 1934 (Box 1)
  - Biographical data, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - List of translations of documents already in the Karen Horney Papers, undated (Box 1)
  - Kursstunde [German original], undated (Box 1)
  - Female Psychology Lectures III, IV, V, VI, VII, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Weitre Fragen Der Weiblichen Psychologie [German original and first draft of translation], 1932 (Box 1)
  - Abitur examination results [translation of German original previously given to Horney Papers], undated (Box 1)
  - New Ways in Psychoanalysis [reviews], 1939 (Box 1)
  - The Neurotic Personality of Our Time [reviews], 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Remarks on Love [German original with translation], undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago paper dealing with material similar to that in lectures on female psychology, undated (Box 1)
  - Woman's Fear of Action, undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries and memorial tributes, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Harold Kelman's account of Karen Horney in response to a request by Joseph Natterson. [includes correspondence], 1964, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Abstracts of talks, essays, lectures, 1942, undated (Box 1)
  - FBI files on Karen Horney [obtained through FOIA request in 1984-1988], 1941-1954 (Box 1)
  - Grote, Louis [photographs and letter from his daughter], 1914, 1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Doctoral dissertation [in German, photocopy], 1915 (Box 1)
  - Material by and about Horney from files of the American Institute for Psychoanalysis, 1946-1950, 1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Notes from interviews conducted by Bernard J. Paris, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Patterson, Renate Horney [includes interview notes and copies of correspondence], 1972, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
  - Eckardt, Marianne Horney [includes interview notes and copies of correspondence], 1976, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of letters from Karen Horney to her daughter Brigitte Horney, 1945-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Existence and Location of Originals
    Photocopies of originals in an archives in Germany.
    - English translations, 1945-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      The numbers in the upper left of the translations indicate Bernard Paris's educated guess as to the letter's place in the chronological sequence; the numbers on the bottom right indicate the sequence in which the letters came to him.
  - Diaries, #1, Notebook on Children, English translation, 1912-1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, #3-5, unpublished portions of adolescent diaries, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, #6: Ego Notebook, English translation, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jack Rubins interview notes [photocopies and transcriptions, also photocopies of correspondence and notes used as background material]
    - Key to the symbols, undated (Box 1)
    - Unidentified people, undated (Box 1)
    - Brief interviews, 1973-1975, undated (Box 1)
    - Barbu, Valer, undated (Box 1)
    - Barshall, Leonard, undated (Box 1)
    - Bieber, Irving, undated (Box 1)
    - Blitsten, Dorothy, undated (Box 1)
    - Bonime, Walter, undated (Box 1)
    - Boss, Medard, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Burnatschki, Kathleen, undated (Box 1)
    - Clemmens, Elizabeth, undated (Box 1)
    - Crane, Sawahara [Mrs. Cornelius], undated (Box 1)
    - Crowley, Ralph, undated (Box 1)
    - Daniels, George, undated (Box 1)
    - DeMartino, ________, undated (Box 1)
    - DeRosis, Louis, undated (Box 1)
    - Durham, Else, undated (Box 1)
    - Eckardt, Marianne, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Ephron, Harmon, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Grinker, Roy, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Harte, B. Joan, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Honroth-Welte, Rita, undated (Box 1)
    - Hulbeck, Charles, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Isenberg, M., undated (Box 1)
    - Kardiner, Abraham, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Kelman, Norman, undated (Box 1)
    - Kornreich, Karl, undated (Box 1)
    - Kubie, Lawrence, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Lancaster, Elizabeth, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Lederer-Eckardt, Gertrude, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Levy, Marie, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Lewin, George, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Lorand, S., 1972 (Box 1)
    - Lowenfeld, Henry, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Lussheimer, Paul, undated (Box 1)
    - Marcus, Ellie, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Marmor, Judd, 1971, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Martin, Alexander, undated (Box 1)
    - Marx, Eugene, undated (Box 1)
    - Mead, Margaret, undated (Box 1)
    - Moulton, Ruth, undated (Box 1)
    - Muller-Braunschweig, Hans, 1972, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Oberndorf, C., undated (Box 1)
    - Patterson, Renate Mintz, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Pisetski, J., 1972 (Box 1)
    - Pizitz, Frances, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Portnoy, Isidore, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Remarque, Paulette Goddard, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Rose, S., undated (Box 1)
    - Schachtel, Ernst, 1973, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Seidermann, Herta, undated (Box 1)
    - Shapiro, Lester, undated (Box 1)
    - Speigel, Rose, undated (Box 1)
    - Spritzer, Esther P., 1977 (Box 1)
    - Sugarman, Katie Kelman, undated (Box 1)
    - Swarinski, Brigitte, undated (Box 1)
    - Tannenbaum, Rose Landers, undated (Box 1)
    - Thompson, Clara, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Tillich, Hannah, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Von Eckardt, Ursula, undated (Box 1)
    - Weigert, Edith, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Weiss, Gertrude, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Wenkart, Simon, undated (Box 1)
    - Westcott, Barbara, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Wolf, Alex, undated (Box 1)
    - Zucker, Gary, undated (Box 1)
    - Zuger, Bernard, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Audio recordings
    - Bernard Paris's interviews with Wanda Willig, Walter Bonime, Norman Kelman, Abe Pinsky, Sara Sheiner [5 cassettes], 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Human Nature Can Change," with Harold Kelman, Fredrich Weiss, Paul Tillich, and Karen Horney [1 cassette of Town Meeting radio program], undated (Box 2)
    - Analytic technique [Horney's last lecture course, copies of original wire recordings on 10 cassettes], 1952 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1946-1952; Accession 2000-M-092
  - Notebooks of Horney's courses at the American Institute of Psychoanalysis [created by Sara Sheiner]
    - Technique, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Interval meetings, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Dream seminar, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Therapy, 1952 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-111
  - Lazarus, What's Next? A Memoir, by Renate Horney [anecdotes about Karen Horney by her daughter], 1999 (Box 1)